<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties most gracious speech together with the Lord Chancellors, to both Houses of Parliament, on Monday, October 27. 1673. By his Majesties special command.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3178A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R175750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52529439</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52529439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178723</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02099)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178723)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2768:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties most gracious speech together with the Lord Chancellors, to both Houses of Parliament, on Monday, October 27. 1673. By his Majesties special command.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1621-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by Andrew Anderson, printer to the Kings most excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title vignette: royal coat of arms and initials C R.</note>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: creased with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dutch War, 1672-1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178723:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>His Majeſties MOST GRACIOUS SPEECH Together with the Lord Chancellors, To both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, On <hi>Monday, October</hi> 27. 1673.</p>
            <p>By His <hi>Majeſties</hi> ſpecial command.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by ANDREW ANDERSON, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſty.</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CUM PRIVILEGIO.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:178723:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:178723:3"/>
            <head>His Majeſties Moſt Gracious SPEECH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Thought this day to have welcomed You with an honourable Peace; My preparations for the War, and Condeſcentions at the Treaty, gave <hi>Me</hi> great reaſon to believe ſo; but the <hi>Dutch</hi> have diſappointed <hi>Me</hi> in that expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and have treated <hi>My</hi> Ambaſſadors at <hi>Cologne,</hi> with the Contempt of Conquerors, and not as might be expected from men in their Condition.</p>
            <p>They have other thoughts then Peace.</p>
            <p>This obligeth <hi>Me</hi> to move you again for a Supply, the Safety and Honor of the Nation neceſſarily requiring it: It muſt be one propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the Occaſion; and I muſt tell you beſides, that if I have it not ſpeedily, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:178723:4"/>Miſchief will be irreparable in <hi>My</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for the next Spring: The Great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioene I have had of you Gentlemen of the Houſe of Commons, will not ſuffer <hi>Me</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Artifices of Our Enemies can poſsibly divert you from giving <hi>Me</hi> this Supply, or that you canfail of adjuſting the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of it.</p>
            <p>I hope I need not uſe many words to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you that I am ſteady in maintaining all the Profeſsions and Promiſes I have made you concerning Religion and Property: And I ſhall be very ready to give you freſh inſtances of <hi>My</hi> Zeal, for preſerving the establiſht Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Lawes, as often as any occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, I am highly concerned to commend to your conſideration and Care the Debt I owe the <hi>Goldſmiths,</hi> in which very many other of <hi>My</hi> good Subjects are involved; I heartily recommend their condition to you, and deſire your aſsiſtance for their relief.</p>
            <p>There is more that I would have you infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of, which I leave to the Chancellor.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:178723:5"/>
            <head>THE Lord Chancellors SPEECH To Both Houſes of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords, and you the Knights, Citizens and Burgeſſes of the Houſe of Commons.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is <hi>Majeſty</hi> had reaſon to expect, That He mould have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Olive-Branch</hi> of <hi>Peace:</hi> His <hi>Naval Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> greater then in any former years, together with the <hi>Land Forces</hi> He had ready for any Occaſion, gave Him aſſurance to obtain it before this time. And the rather, becauſe His aims were not <hi>Conquest,</hi> unleſs by obſtinacy inforced; But His <hi>Condeſcentions</hi> at the Treaty have been ſo great, That the very <hi>Mediators</hi> have declared they were not reaſonably to be refuſed. He could not be <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſecuring the <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> of His <hi>Own Seas;</hi> The firſt by an Article clear and not eluſory of the <hi>Flagg;</hi> The other by an Article that preſerved the right of the <hi>Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> but gave the <hi>Dutch</hi> permiſſion, as Tenants, under a ſmall Rent, to enjoy, and continue that <hi>gainful Trade</hi> upon His Coaſts. <hi>The King</hi> was obliged, for the <hi>Security</hi> of a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:178723:6"/>laſting Peace, as alſo by the Laws of <hi>Gratitude,</hi> and <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Houſe of Orange</hi> ſetled, and the <hi>Lovestein,</hi> that <hi>Carthaginian</hi> party, brought down. Neither in this did the <hi>King</hi> inſiſt beyond what was moderate, and agreeable to their Government: And what the Princes anceſtors enjoyed amongſt them. Beſides theſe, there was neceſſary to the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> that there ſhould be a fair <hi>Adjustment</hi> of <hi>Commerce</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies;</hi> where the Kings Demands were reaſonable, and according to the Law of Nations; and <hi>their Practice</hi> of late years hath been <hi>Exorbitant,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſsive,</hi> ſuitable onely to their Power and Intereſt, and <hi>destructive,</hi> if continued, to our <hi>Eaſt-India-Company.</hi> Theſe were all, of any moment, the King inſiſted on; as judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aright, That that <hi>Peace</hi> that was <hi>reaſonable, juſt,</hi> and <hi>fair</hi> to both parties, would be <hi>ſacred</hi> and <hi>durable.</hi> And that by this means, He ſhould depreſs the Intereſt, and Reputation of that <hi>Loveſtein</hi> party amongſt them, who ſucked in with their milk an inveterate hatred to <hi>England,</hi> and tranſmit it to their poſterity, as a <hi>diſtinguiſhing Character,</hi> wherein they place their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to their <hi>Country.</hi> In return to this <hi>Candid,</hi> and <hi>fair proceeding on the Kings part,</hi> His Majeſty aſſures you he hath received <hi>nothing,</hi> but the moſt <hi>ſcornful,</hi> and <hi>contemptuous treatment</hi> imaginable; Papers delivered in to the <hi>Medatiors,</hi> owned by them to beſtuffed with ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſome Language, that they were <hi>aſhamed</hi> and <hi>refuſed</hi> to ſhew them. Never agreeing to any Article about the <hi>Flagg,</hi> that was clear or plain: Refuſing any Article of the <hi>Fiſhing,</hi> but ſuch a one, as might ſell them the right of Inheritance, for an inconſiderable ſum of money, though it be a <hi>Royalty</hi> ſo <hi>inherent in the Crown of England,</hi> that I may ſay, (with His Majeſties pardon for the Expreſsion) He cannot ſell it. The Article of the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> and the <hi>Adjuſtment</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt-India-Trade</hi> had neither of them any better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; And to make all of a piece, they have this laſt week ſent a Trumpetter with an Addreſs to His Majeſty, being a deduction of their ſeveral Offers of Peace, as they call them, and their deſires for it now; but it is both in the Penning and the Timeing of it, plainly an Appeal to His Majeſties People againſt Himſelf; And the King hath commanded me to tell you, He is reſolved to joyn iſſue with them, and Print both their Addreſs, and His Anſwer, that His People and the World may ſee how notorious falſhoods and ſlights
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:178723:7"/>they endeavour to put upon Him. In a word, in <hi>England,</hi> and in all <hi>other Places,</hi> and to all <hi>other Perſons</hi> of the World, they declare they <hi>offer all things</hi> to obtain a Peace from the King of <hi>England:</hi> But to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> His <hi>Miniſters,</hi> the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ators,</hi> or <hi>His Plenipotentiaries,</hi> it may with confidence and truth be affirmed, that to this day; nay, even in this laſt Addreſs they have <hi>offered nothing.</hi> They deſire the Kings Subjects would believe they <hi>beg</hi> for <hi>Peace,</hi> whilſt their <hi>true requeſt</hi> is, onely to be permitted to be once <hi>Masters of the Seas;</hi> Which they hope, if they can ſubſiſt at Land, length of time may give them: And if once <hi>got,</hi> is never to be <hi>loſt;</hi> Nor can it be <hi>bought</hi> by any State or Empire, <hi>at too great a rate.</hi> And what Security their <hi>Agreement</hi> with us <hi>in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> will afford when they ſhall have the Power, former Inſtances may give <hi>Demonſtration of. Joynt Intereſts</hi> have often ſecured the Peace of <hi>differing Religions,</hi> but <hi>agreeing Profeſsions</hi> hath hardly an example of preſerving the Peace of <hi>different Intereſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the true and natural ſtate of things, His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> doth with great <hi>aſsurance</hi> throw Himſelf into the Arms <hi>of You His Parliament,</hi> for <hi>a Supply</hi> ſuitable to this great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair He is engaged in. When you conſider we are an <hi>Iſland,</hi> 'tis not <hi>Riches</hi> nor <hi>Greatneſs</hi> we contend for; yet thoſe muſt attend the <hi>Succeſs;</hi> But 'tis our <hi>very Beings</hi> are in queſtion: We ſight <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. We are no longer <hi>Freemen,</hi> being <hi>Iſlanders,</hi> and <hi>Neighbours,</hi> if they <hi>Maſter us at Sea.</hi> There is not ſo lawful or commendable a <hi>jealouſie</hi> in the World, as an <hi>Engliſhmans,</hi> of the growing Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of any <hi>Prince or State at Sea.</hi> If you permit the <hi>Sea, our Britiſh Wife,</hi> to be <hi>raviſhed,</hi> an eternal mark of <hi>Infamy</hi> will <hi>ſtick upon us;</hi> Therefore I am commanded earneſtly to recommend to you not onely the <hi>Proportion,</hi> but the <hi>Time</hi> of the <hi>Supply.</hi> For unleſs you think of it <hi>early,</hi> it will not be ſerviceable to the chief end of ſetting out a <hi>Fleet betimes</hi> the <hi>next Spring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the next part of the <hi>Kings Speech,</hi> I can add nothing to what His Majeſty hath ſaid. For as to <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> His <hi>heart</hi> is with your <hi>heart, perfectly with your heart:</hi> He hath not yet learned to deny you any thing; and He believes your <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> is ſuch, He never ſhall. He asks of you to be at <hi>Peace in Him,</hi> as He is <hi>in You,</hi> and He ſhall <hi>never deceive you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:178723:8"/>
            <p>There is one word more, I am commanded to ſay concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Debt</hi> is owing to the <hi>Goldſmiths.</hi> The King holds himſelf in <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> obliged to ſee them ſatisfied. Beſides, you all know how many <hi>Widows, Orphans,</hi> and <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons,</hi> the publick Calamity hath overtaken; and how hard it is, that ſo <hi>diſproportionable a burthen</hi> ſhould fall upon them, even to their utter <hi>Ruine.</hi> The whole Caſe is ſo well and generally known, that I need ſay no more. Your <hi>great Wiſdoms</hi> hath not done it at the firſt, peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that the Trade of the <hi>Banker</hi> might be <hi>ſuppreſſed;</hi> which end is now attained. So that now your <hi>great Goodneſs</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to thoſe poor people, and the many innocent ones that are concerned with them, ſome life and aſſurance of Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a competent time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lords and Gentlemen,</hi> I have no more in command, and therefore ſhall conclude with my own hearty Prayers, That this <hi>Seſsion</hi> may <hi>equal,</hi> nay <hi>exceed</hi> the honour of the laſt; That it may perfect what the laſt begun for the <hi>Safety of this King,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> That it may be ever famous for having eſtabliſhed, upon a durable Foundation, our <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Laws, and Properties;</hi> That we may not be toſſed with <hi>boiſterous Winds,</hi> nor overtaken by a <hi>ſudden dead Calm:</hi> But that a <hi>gentle fair Gale</hi> may carry you in a ſteady, even, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved way into the Ports of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Security.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
